{"tossups": [{"question": "The Gran Reunion Lodge was founded in this country, which was where an envoy of the Supreme Junta of Caracas, Luis L\u00f3pez M\u00e9ndez, recruited mercenaries. This country was the birthplace of an adventurer who attracted colonists to a made-up kingdom ruled by George Frederic Augustus, as well as a leader of an amphibious nighttime assault on Valdivia. This country launched two failed invasions of (*) Buenos Aires in 1806 and 1807, and this country\u2019s namesake \u201clegions\u201d played critical roles in the battles of Boyaca and Carabobo. After the fall of the Second Venuzuelan Republic, Sim\u00f3n Bol\u00edvar wrote a \"letter\u201d named after a colony of this country. For 10 points, name this country, whose citizens provided support to Latin American revolutionaries during the Prime Ministership of Lord Castlereagh.\u00a0", "answer": "Great Britain (accept United Kingdom; accept British Legions; accept Scotland; prompt on \u201cJamaica\u201d by asking, \u201cWhich was a colony of what country?\u201d. The Brits in the second line are, respectively, Gregor McGregor and Thomas Cochrane.)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The amazingly-named advocate for Confederation Amor de Cosmos founded a still-extant business in this industry in Victoria, B.C. before becoming the province\u2019s second premier. In 1880, a former politician and owner of a company in this industry in Toronto was shot and killed by a disgruntled employee. A leader in this industry in Upper Canada brought together former Reform politicians and Clear (*) Grits to form the Liberal Party of Canada. The founder of a major company in this industry used his company to build opposition to Robert Borden\u2019s government in Quebec as the leader of Francophone opposition to conscription during World War I. George Brown and Henri Bourassa were leaders in, for 10 points, what industry which is still dominated by Le Devoir and The Globe and Mail?", "answer": "newspaper (prompt on \u201cmedia\u201d or answers involving media that don\u2019t specify newspapers)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In a now-discredited account, the Chronica Elini claims that an institution in this city was founded by a representative of each of Catholicism, Greek Orthodoxy, Judaism, and Islam, including the historically-known Shabbatai Donnolo. Prince Guaimar IV of this city was assassinated on the orders of his four brothers-in-law, leading to their rule of the city for only seven days. A woman from this city was described as \u201clike another Pallas, if not a second Athena\u201d for leading troops with her husband at the Battle of Dyrrhachium. This city, home of Sikelgaita, was also the origin of three texts known as the (*) Trotula, one of which describes how to enhance women\u2019s beauty through cosmetics and hair- and skincare. The large collection of Arabic texts held at Monte Cassino gave access to the works of classical physicians to a medical school in this city before the rest of Western Europe. For 10 points, name this southern Italian city, a center for medieval medicine.", "answer": "Salerno", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A settlement sometimes known as Fuyck (\u201cfake\u201d) on this river was the scene of a power struggle between a large private landholder and a trading company, which ended when nine armed representatives of the company took command of the local fort. This was the largest river on which land grants were given to those who could settle at least 50 adults through the Charter of Freedoms and Exemptions. The near destruction of the town of Pavonia on this river was one in a series of conflicts that escalated into (*) Kieft\u2019s War. A neighborhood in a city on the east bank of this river is named after the farms, or bouwerij (bough-vair-eye), of its first European settlers. It was primarily along this river that landholders called patroons settled, the most famous of which was Kiliaen van Rensselaer. For 10 points, identify this river in modern New York, the center of Dutch colonization of North America.", "answer": "Hudson River", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A document from this culture, now named after Alexander Rhind, contains a table showing ways of writing fractions that could be written as 2/n as the sum of fractions with numerators of one. Mathematical documents from this culture often framed multiplication and division problems as calculating the strength of bread or beer. This culture solved for unknown variables, known as aha, via the method of false position, such as when calculating the seked of hypotenuses. A now-disputed interpretation of a symbol from this culture claims that it was used to measure small volumes as fractions of a (*) hekat. That symbol supposedly represents the fractions between 1/2 and 1/64 with denominators of powers of two and depicts the eye of a falcon. For 10 points, what is this culture whose mythology claims was taught mathematics by Thoth?", "answer": "Ancient Egypt", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Orogeny on this continent during the Miocene led to a series of algal blooms that poisoned the marine life found at \u201cWhale Hill\u201d. Instead of indicating the presence of a trunk, the retracted nostrils of Macrauchenia, which lived on this continent, may have been an adaptation to browsing on thorny plants. On this continent, the bones of smaller ungulate species from the orders Litopterna and Notoungulata have been found in the nests of Phorusrhacids. The Australidelphian (*) marsupials originated on this continent, though are now only represented there by the monito del monte. A \u201cGreat Interchange\u201d involving this continent 2-3 million years ago featured animals like gomphotheres, wolves, and deer moving [emphasize] to it and animals like glyptodonts, ground sloths, and opossums moving [emphasize] from it. For 10 points, identify this continent, which saw a massive change in its wildlife once connected with its northern neighbor via the Isthmus of Panama.", "answer": "South America", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Sir John Maynard likely skirted restrictions on this activity because of Cromwell\u2019s hate of the Spanish, while Robert Cox resorted to bribes and drolls to avoid it.\u00a0 Men like Charles Hart, Nicolas Burt, and William Robbins joined the royalist cause in the English Civil War because of restrictions placed on this activity. Thomas Becon opposed this activity because of the similarities he saw to rituals of the Catholic Church. Along with denouncing celebrations like Christmas, William Prynne wrote a 1000-page-long text which opposed this kind of activity called (*) Histriomastix. Support for restrictions on this activity often focused on the perceived immorality of cross-dressing young men, who were used because women were not permitted to participate until the reign of Charles II. For 10 points, identify this policy enacted by the Long Parliament and maintained under Lord Protector Oliver Cromwell, whose repeal led to the era of Restoration Comedy.", "answer": "theatre or acting (accept any answers involving live performance)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable Though they directly possessed it, one group preferred to claim this status by calling themselves the \u201cGurganiya\u201d, following the example of a man who used Saray Mulk Khan to try to obtain it. Dispute over Hafsa Sultan has thrown doubts on whether Suleiman I held this status. Because he did not possess this status, one ruler styled himself as an emir in the service of the puppet ruler Suyurghatmish. The abduction of a woman by the (*) Merkits is the source of debate for whether one man had this status. A 2003 study by Zerjal et al asserts that a Y-chromosome lineage present in about 16 million men in Asia is due in large part to the conquests of the man responsible for this status. For 10 points, what is this status that B\u00f6rte helped give to Chagatai, \u00d6gedei, and possibly Jochi?", "answer": "descent from Genghis Khan (accept any answer about Genghis\u2019 progeny, e.g. Genghisids, sons/daughters/children of Genghis Khan, etc.; accept Tem\u00fcjin, Chingis Khan, or Chingiz Khan, in place of \u201cGenghis Khan\u201d; prompt on answers suggesting a familial relationship to, but not direct descent from, Genghis Khan; antiprompt on answers referring to more specific lineages, e.g. any of his sons\u2019/grandsons\u2019 lines)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "As a lawyer, a former governor of this state bizarrely claimed that governors had \u201cthe divine right of kings\u201d; that man, nicknamed \u201cPrivate Joe\u201d, was serving another governor of this state who had deposited state funds in a private bank he owned while state treasurer. A governor of this state spent the last years of his life advocating for prison reform after heading a 1968 federal commission that published an ambitious report that was purchased by over two million people. That commission, which investigated the causes of recent African-American race riots in (*) Detroit, also investigated the first Puerto-Rican riots in American history in this state\u2019s Division Street riots. During the 1960s, Otto Kerner was governor of this state, the first in four of its governors to be imprisoned for charges of corruption. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by Dan Walker, James R. Thompson, and Rod Blagojevich.", "answer": "Illinois", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The Krobo people applied their tradition of collective farming, called huza, to this commodity, becoming early leaders in its production. This commodity saw an increase in use relative to competing products due to its use in [emphasize] producing the mass-marketed Sunlight brand. This commodity saw an expansion in production following the development of a more productive dura variety at Deli (day-lee). William Lever was given a concession from the Belgian Congo to found a namesake town for the production of this commodity, and under his (*) Huileries du Congo Belge Company, eventually a soap factory. Particularly after the abolition of the British slave trade, the Kingdoms of Bonny and Calabar were early centers for the trade of this commodity. For 10 points, identify this commodity, the cultivation of which provided a colonial-era name for the coast around the Niger Delta.", "answer": "palm oil (do not accept or prompt on just \u201coil\u201d)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A book about the rampant drug use in this leader\u2019s country is titled \u201cthis leader\u2019s Little Helper\u201d. A doctor attempted to persuade this leader to personally endorse the regimen of Vitamultin so the company he had a 50% stake in could market it. Novelist Norman Ohler is best known for a heavily-criticized book about drug use in this leader\u2019s country. This leader was personally injected by doctor Thomas Morrell with bizarre \u201cmedicines\u201d like Orchikrin, derived from (*) bull\u2019s testicles, and psycho-active drugs like cocaine and morphine. Soldiers in this leader\u2019s army were administered millions of tablets of Pertivin, a form of methamphetamine, during an invasion of its eastern neighbour. A high-profile trial, which found that this leader and his party had permitted chemical and pharmaceutical conglomerate IG Farben to use slave labour, was held in 1948.\u00a0 For 10 points, name this leader of a country that heavily abused drugs during Operation Barbarossa.", "answer": "Adolf Hitler", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s W\u00e0ngl\u00f3ngm\u00e9n district was home to a notorious \u201cMilitary and Statistics Bureau\u201d, or J\u016bnt\u01d2ng, which coordinated the assassination of T\u00e1ng Sh\u00e0oy\u00ed. It\u2019s not in the Middle East, but Patrick Hurley was Franklin Roosevelt\u2019s personal representative in this city. While working in this city, Sir Archibald Kerr helped broker a meeting between one leader and Jawaharlal Nehru. Frequent bombing raids on this city led it to be dubbed the \u201cCity of Heroes\u201d, and American general (*) \u201cVinegar Joe\u201d Stilwell was based in this city. After an assault on his previous capital, Nanjing, Chiang Kai-Shek relocated his Nationalist forces to this city during the Second Sino-Japanese war. For 10 points, name this city formerly in Sichuan and now a directly administered municipality, the wartime capital of the Republic of China from 1937 to 1945.", "answer": "Ch\u00f3ngq\u00ecng (accept Chungking)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "ANSWER: Ch\u00f3ngq\u00ecng (accept Chungking) <LL> \u00a0 13. A 2009 paper by Heinemeier et al used an olive branch to date an event named after this civilization, improving upon multiple prior dating methods, including the use of lentils and faba beans. The ancient world\u2019s largest known wine cellar was in use during a period of this civilization\u2019s influence at the site of Tel Kabri. Population displacements caused by an event named after this civilization ended bicameral thought according to Julian Jaynes. Artists from this civilization created the Fisherman and (*) Ship Frescoes. Robert Ritner suggests that the conditions described in the Bamboo Annals concerning the fall of the Xi\u00e0 dynasty could be attributed to an event named after this civilization, which preserved its town of Akrotiri. For 10 points, an eruption on the island of Thera is also named after which Bronze Age civilization based on Crete?", "answer": "Minoan culture", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The murder trial of a woman killed by her husband for an affair with a priest in Tarakeswar prompted a wave of social and political critique in this region. Abuses by the local zamindar such as a beard tax led Titumir to rebel in 1831 in this region, becoming an icon of resistance with his death. An unsuccessful attempt to assassinate magistrate Douglas Kingsford was carried out by the Anushilan Samiti, one of several terrorist cells that arose in this region in the early 20th century. Access to Western education in the 19th century created a new elite class in this region known as the bhadralok (bhuh-druh-loak), many of which participated in (*) Hindu reform movements like Ram Mohan Roy\u2019s Brahmo Sabha. In 1911, this region was reunited after extensive backlash against its 1905 Partition. For 10 points, political and social unrest challenged British control in what region of eastern South Asia governed from Calcutta?", "answer": "Bengal (accept West/East Bengal)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A queen of this kingdom who hated both the sea and cats was ironically the wife of the first of its four \u201cship-kings\u201d and was distrusted by the people for making several cats into her spies. Two brothers who jointly ruled this kingdom are commemorated at the northern end of Nen Hithoel. King Tarondor of this kingdom moved to a new city following the devastation of the old capital during the Great Plague. For his assistance in fending off the Balchoth, a region in the north of this kingdom was ceded to (*) \u00a0Eorl the Young. Following the death of the childless King E\u00e4rnur (ay-ar-noor), Mardil ruled this kingdom as the first of the line of Stewards. In a film adaptation, a siege of the capital of this kingdom is relieved by an army of the dead who had been cursed by King Isildur. The last successor of N\u00famenor, for 10 points, identify this kingdom, ruled from Minas Tirith during The Lord of the Rings.", "answer": "Kingdom of Gondor (accept South-kingdom)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Juan Pardo established Fort San Juan near this culture\u2019s town of Joara (hwah-rah), the first Spanish settlement away from the coast in that region. A burial at this culture\u2019s Spiro site was compared to King Tut\u2019s tomb for the vast number of artifacts found there, most notably perishable wood, textiles, and shells. A copper-covered cedar mask was found at this culture\u2019s Emmons Cemetery Site. Both Ilex vomitoria and the lightning whelk shells it was served in were traded hundreds of miles to reach this culture\u2019s largest site. Increased social stratification and more elaborate burials are archaeological traces of the assimilation of the (*) Caddoan peoples into this culture. Hernando de Soto encountered the latest surviving people of this culture as he traveled through the southeastern US. For 10 points, name this Native American culture whose largest site was Cahokia.", "answer": "Mississippian culture", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An unused plan to lift a siege of this region\u2019s capital involved selling the besieging army cloth infected with the bubonic plague. Members of the Gradonico family were influential in the Revolt of St. Titus in this region, suppressed by Luchino dal Verme. The final Muslim ruler of this region, known as Kouroupas in Byzantine sources, was captured following Nikephoros II Phokas\u2019 capture of Chandax. Early colonial settlement of this region founded the city of Chania over the Classical settlement of Kydonia. Power moved away from the city of Gortyn during Muslim rule of this region. Following the (*) Fourth Crusade, Boniface of Montferrat traded this region to acquire Thessaloniki. Venetian rule of this region ended with the 21-year siege of its capital Candia, now the city of Heraklion. For 10 points, what is this large Greek island of the southern Aegean Sea?", "answer": "Crete (accept Kr\u00edti)", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An early settlement in this country was attacked by a chieftain given the name \u201cKing Joe Harris\u201d, and in their counterattack, the settlers enlisted another chieftain, \u201cBob Gray\u201d. The towns of Arthington and Brewerville were founded to augment this country\u2019s power in its interior. In response to British and French colonial interest in the area, the first president of this country, Joseph Jenkins Roberts, traveled along the coast, signing friendship treaties with the local chieftains as he went. After a failed attempt to force the Kru people from their land, a country named after (*) Maryland joined this country. For most of its existence, this country was politically dominated by the True Whig Party, composed mostly of the descendants of freed slaves. For 10 points, name this West African country founded with the help of the American Colonization Society.", "answer": "Liberia", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Roman houses found in this modern country include the trifolium villa and the Villa of the Hunters. The mostly-intact Lucinian baths were built in a city in this modern country, which emerged from a Roman pagus and a native civitas called Dougga; in that city, Christians destroyed temples to Saturn and Juno Caelestis. A fast-growing city in this modern country was founded as (*) Colonia Junonia after initial plans set by Julius Caesar. A heresy centered in this modern country which believed the church should not include \u201ctraditors\u201d was led by Donatus Magnus. Along with Ravenna, a city in this modern country was the capital of a Byzantine province called an Exarchate; that state was set up after Belisarius conquered the capital of Genseric\u2019s Vandal Kingdom, which was in this modern country. For 10 points, name this modern country in Africa where Rome rebuilt the ancient city of Carthage.", "answer": "Republic of Tunisia", "category": "History"}, {"question": "150 men of this tribe joined General Ferdinand Claiborne in the Battle of Econochaca and destroyed a camp established by Josiah Francis. In the 1740\u2019s, this tribe fought a civil war between the French-leaning Okla Tannap and the British-leaning Okla Falaya. A chieftain of this tribe, Pushmataha, refused to ally with Tecumseh, citing the prosperity and technological gains of their relations with the US. \u00a0A statue dedicated in 2017 in Midleton, Ireland commemorates a donation this tribe made to those suffering in the Irish Potato Famine. With the Treaty of (*) Dancing Rabbit Creek, this tribe was the first to be dislocated under the Indian Removal Act. For 10 points, what is this tribe, which, along with the Seminole, Creek, Chickasaw, and Cherokee, was one of the \u201cFive Civilized Tribes\u201d?", "answer": "Choctaw (accept Chahta)", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}